Finding Aid for United States Army Signal Corps photograph collection 1918-1919
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
United States Army Signal Corps photograph collection, 1918-1919
United States. Army. Signal Corps.
1 linear feet
Photographs taken during the Polar Bear Expedition to northern Russia, and accumulated by several veterans; include scenes of American soldiers in camp and on patrol, of life in Archangel and in Russian villages, and of battlefields, fortifications, armored trains, ships, airplanes, burial rites, and graves. Also includes a list of photographs and their captions.
921010 UCa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Signal Corps photo collection was compiled from a number of individual donors.
The collection is open for research.
About 185 photographs. The photographs include scenes of life in Archangel, armored trains, villages, port facilities, rural life, men in barracks, fortifications, prisoners, group portraits, men on patrol and in camp, the railroad, an airplane, burials, and graves. Also included is a "List of official U.S. photographs illustrative of the activities of the North Russian Expeditionary Force" which contains descriptions, including names and locations, of ca. 575 Signal Corps photos, arranged by photo number.
Subjects
Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; World War, 1914-1918.; Polar Bear Expedition (1918-1919); Airplanes.; Death.; Funeral rites and ceremonies.; Military facilities.; Military life.; Packtrains.; Railroads--Russia (Federation); Reindeer.; Ships.; War casualties.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Papers
  - "List of official U.S. photographs illustrative of the activities of the North Russian Expeditionary Force" (Folder 1)
- Photographs
  The photographs are arranged in by Signal Corps print number, which are approximately chronological, though there are occasional discrepancies. The collection contains only a portion of all photos taken by the Signal Corps. The listing below includes only descriptions of prints in Bentley Library's Signal Corps collection. There is one folder of unnumbered photos. Most of the numbered photos are 6 1/2" x 8 1/2" prints, but there are 41 prints 10 3/4" x 13 3/4" in size.
  - Print Nos. 13814-32075, 19 prints (Folder 2)
    - Print No. 13814, unidentified (Item 1)
    - Print No. 13819, unidentified (Item 2)
    - Print No. 23074, unidentified (Item 3)
    - Print No. 28597 September 6, 1918 (Item 4)
      (Sailors from the U.S.S., Olympia, who formed a part of a landing force, returning from the line along the railroad to Vologda where they had been fighting Bolsheviks. The party got back to its starting point only after picking its way through swamps and forests. They were compelled to abandon everything but their rifles. They are surrounded by men of the 339th Infantry, who had just landed in Russia. Bakharitza, Russia.)
    - Print No. 28599 September 6, 1918 (Item 5)
      (One hundred and twenty three Bolshevik prisoners, captured by the French fighting along the railroad between Archangel and Vologda, being counted on their arrival at Bakharitza by an American soldier and a sailor from the U.S.S. Olympia. The prisoners were brought to Archangel under guard of American sailors. Bakharitza, Russia.)
    - Print No. 28601 September 6, 1918 (Item 6)
      (Unloading first American Red Cross ambulances on the docks at Bakharitza. Bakharitza, Russia.)
    - Print No. 28602 September 6, 1918 (Item 7)
      (Convoy of the three ships which carried first American troops to Russia. Left to right: H.M.T. Somoli, flagship; H.M.T. Tydeus; and H.M.T. Nagoya. Bakharitza, Russia.)
    - Print No. 28607 September 18, 1918 (Item 8)
      (French, British, and American officers paying tribute to Lieut. Marchs T. Casey in cemetery. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 28616 September 29, 1918 (Item 9)
      (Home-knit socks strung up to dry over a camp fire at the edge of a forest, through which men of Company M, 339th Inf. pick their way for 17 hours, in a vain attempt to outflank the Bolsheviks farther down the railroad. A great part of the march was through mud and swamp. Obozerskaya, Russia.)
    - Print No. 28617 September 29, 1916 (Item 10)
      (Company M, 339th Inf. after resting an hour, following the 17 hours march through the woods and swamps, set out again for the front. They are seen in this picture starting out along the railroad line. One of the armored cars use by the Allies is seen in the distance. Obozerskaya, Russia.)
    - Print No. 28618 September 29, 1918 (Item 11)
      (Advance American outpost on guard near the American headquarters along the railroad, a mile from the scene of actual fighting. Obozerskaya, Russia.)
    - Print No. 32053 September 21, 1918 (Item 12)
      (Graves of first three American soldiers killed in action on the North Russian front. September 16, 1918. Left to right: Ignacy H. Kwasniewski, Mechanic, Co. I; Anthony Soczkoski; Pvt, Co. I; and Phillip Sokol, Pvt.; Co. I; all of the 339th Regiment Infantry. Obozerskaya Russia.)
    - Print No. 32054 September 21, 1918 (Item 13)
      (Bolshevik wooden gun mount, used for anti-aircraft guns, found at Obozerskaya, Russia)
    - Print No. 32056 September 21, 1918 (Item 14)
      (Station used as temporary Red Cross hospital by the Allied forces. Obozerskaya, Russia)
    - Print No. 32057 September 21, 1918 (Item 15)
      (American cooks preparing supper for the troops near the front. Obozerskaya, Russia)
    - Print No. 32065 October l 1918 (Item 16)
      (Final rites. Taps being blown at the conclusion of the funeral services of Schlioma Dyment, of Company M, 339th Regt. Inf. Obozerskaya, Russia.)
    - Print No. 32067 September 24, 1918 (Item 17)
      (Russian, English, and Cossack soldiers, crew of one of the armored cars. Obozerskaya, Russia)
    - Print No. 32071 September 13, 1918 (Item 18)
      (Finished boards loaded on Russian carts. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 32075 September 27, 1918 (Item 19)
      (Village of Rozjezdnaya at Verst 466. Captured from the Bolshevik forces on September 16, 1918. Rozjezdnaya, Russia.)
  - Print Nos. 34607-39259, 19 prints (Folder 3)
    - Print No. 34607 October 7, 1918 (Item 1)
      (Pvt. George Dhimian, Company G, 339th Inf. and Pvt. Marvin Mock, Co. F, 339th Inf., carrying water in the native fashion from the Dwina River to barracks. It is boiled before using. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 34609 October 7, 1918 (Item 2)
      (Line of natives of Archangel, Russia, waiting to get an allowance of bread. Military authorities provide the civil population who cannot get them otherwise, with certain articles of food. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 34610 October 7, 1918 (Item 3)
      (Office of Regimental Headquarters, 339th Infantry, located in a building in Archangel, Russia, formerly occupied by an up to date technical school. Left to right: Corpl. Clifton B. Knight, Corpl. Frank Wegenka, Pvt. Daniel G. Anderson, Pvt. William Putris, Pvt. Steve Antinoff, Pvt. Herbert G. Dunning, Corpl. Herman Weisberg, Sergt. Maj. Jacob Weiner. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 34629 October 15, 1918 (Item 4)
      (Unloading flour from U. S. cargo boat Ascutney at Archangel, Russia. This boat was built in Seattle, Washington in seventy three days and loaded with nine thousand tons of flour which were brought to Russia on its maiden voyage. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 34631 October 15, 1918 (Item 5)
      (American flour being transferred form holds of freighters at Archangel, Russia to small row boat and sailboats from which it is carried to various points up and down the river.)
    - Print No. 34633 October 16, 1918 (Item 6)
      (Bolshevik prisoners going down one of the streets of Archangel, Russia under American guard. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 39132 October 25, 1918 (Item 7)
      (Two American soldiers from Headquarters Company. 339th Regt. Inf. shopping in market. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 39135 October 27, 1918 (Item 8)
      (Archangel water front, from a tug boat, on river Dwina. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 39147 October 25, 1918 (Item 9)
      (American soldiers and other pedestrians on Troitsky Prospect one of main streets of Archangel, Russia, with one of numerous churches of city in background. The domes of these churches are all inlaid with gold leaf and the tall spires are gilded.)
    - Print No. 39148 October 27, 1918 (Item 10)
      (American soldier, from 2nd Battalion, 339th Regt. Inf., guarding warehouses in which are stored Allied food supplies. Note load of oatmeal ready to be unloaded. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 39150 October 27, 1918 (Item 11)
      (American soldier in special Arctic uniform and woman beggar on steps of church in Archangel, Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 39242 September 6, 1918 (Item 12)
      (Russians preparing land for cultivation. Bakharitza, Russia.)
    - Print No. 39247 September 6, 1918 (Item 13)
      (Members of 339th Regt. Inf. building their headquarters out of logs. Bakharitza, Russia.)
    - Print No. 39251 September 5, 1918 (Item 14)
      (Russian woman with her horse and cart hauling supplies for soldiers. Bakharitza, Russia.)
    - Print No. 39252 September 6, 1918 (Item 15)
      (Transports in harbor after being unloaded. Bakharitza, Russia.)
    - Print No. 39254 September 5, 1918 (Item 16)
      (Soldiers unloading their supplies and equipment from transports. Bakharitza, Russia.)
    - Print No. 39255 September 5, 1918 (Item 17)
      (Troops landing in Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 39258 September 5, 1918 (Item 18)
      (American troops in Russia dis-embarking from H.M. Transport Somali. Bakharitza, Russia.)
    - Print No. 39259 September 5, 1918 (Item 19)
      (Soldiers of 339th Infantry, A.N.R.E.F. leaving dock for camp. Bakharitza, Russia.)
  - Print Nos. 40566-50660, 14 prints (Folder 4)
    - Print No. 40566 November 15, 1918 (Item 1)
      (3rd Bn. Headquarters, housed in a box car. Troops of the 3rd Bn. have been engaged on the Vologda Railroad Front continuously since the day they landed. In the picture right to left: Lieut. Lewis Jahns, Adjt., 2nd Lt. Adolph Anselmi, Signal Officer, Lieut. N.C. Hallock, Intelligence Officer; Corpl. C.J. Barnum, Pvt. J.W. Phillips, Pvt. Harold H. Holliday, Sergt. Maj. Ernest Reed, of Hdqrs. Det.; Verst Railroad line to Vologda, Russia.)
    - Print No. 40577 November 15, 1918 (Item 2)
      (Looking South along the main railroad line from siding at Verst 455. In the foreground is Machine Gun Post (lettered "A" on sketch) which commands tracks. Verst 455, Russia.)
    - Print No. 40585 November 15, 1918 (Item 3)
      (View north along the railroad at Verst 454. At the left is the clearing which gives Blockhouse #1 a direct view of the railroad. In the foreground is the sign giving the Verst No. and to the right of the picture is seen the siding at 455. Verst 455, Russia.)
    - Print No. 40599 November 16, 1918 (Item 4)
      (Men of the Allied armies at the front waiting in line for the opening of the Y.M.C.A. canteen car. Verst 455, Russia.)
    - Print No. 40604 November 16, 1918 (Item 5)
      (Second blockhouse on left of track (looking southeast) Verst 445, Russia.)
    - Print No. 50030 (Item 6)
      [no Signal Corps description provided-soldier by rail fence]
    - Print No. 50099 (Item 7)
      [no Signal Corps description provided-Russian prisoners standing along railroad cars]
    - Print No. 50101 (Item 8)
      [no Signal Corps description provided-Dwina River front Archangel, American Headquarters in center building]
    - Print No. 50103 (Item 9)
      [no Signal Corps description provided-peasants in horse-drawn wagons]
    - Print No. 50302 (Item 10)
      [no Signal Corps description provided-Russian Officers]
    - Print No. 50305 (Item 11)
      [no Signal Corps description provided-American troops marching past Russian officers]
    - Print No. 50648 (Item 12)
      [no Signal Corps description provided-soldiers seated around campfire?]
    - Print No. 50650 (Item 13)
      [no Signal Corps description provided-log building in woods]
    - Print No. 50660 (Item 14)
      [no Signal Corps description provided-guardpost]
  - Print Nos. 152801-152820, 22 prints (Folder 5)
    - Print No. 152751 November 30, 1918 (Item 1)
      (One of the sporting events of the season in Archangel. A boxing bout between color sergt. Anthony Choike, Hdqrs. Co. 339th Inf. welter-weight, champion of the 85th Division and G. Pionnier, one of the champion welter-weights of the French Army. The bout went three rounds before a large crowd in the Y.M.C.A. and ended in a draw. Sgt. Choike, is at the left. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152761 December 9, 1918 (Item 2)
      (Entrance to the 53rd Stationery hospital (English) in which a number of the American soldiers died from the Spanish influenza, soon after the arrival of the first American forces in Archangel. At present venereal cases are being treated in this hospital. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152762 December 9, 1918 (Item 3)
      (Building at Smolny Barracks in which the Hdqrs. of the 2nd Bn. has been set up. Smolny Barracks are located near the Smolny Docks. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152767 December 11, 1918 (Item 4)
      (This picture was taken during the suppression of the mutiny among Russian troops, who had refused to go to the front when ordered. Two companies, quartered in a large white building known as Alexandria Barracks, were given until two o'clock on the afternoon of December 11th to obey the order. Promptly at this time machine gun and rifle fire was directed against the building. British troops surrounded the building on three sides, while Headquarters Company, 339th Infantry held the fourth. In the distance, at the center of the picture can be seen the barracks with the smoke and dust of the trench mortar bomb bursting against the side. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152769 December 11, 1918 (Item 5)
      (Russian soldiers who had refused to go to the front, after a few shots had been fired by American and British troops, who had surrounded the building in which they were quartered, threw down their arms and ran from the building carrying a white flag. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152770 December 11, 1918 (Item 6)
      (Groups of Russian soldiers leaving Alexandria Barracks to surrender to American and British troops who had fired on the building when the Russians had mutinied. Archangel, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152783 December 21, 1918 (Item 7)
      (One of the sights occasionally seen by American soldiers travelling by convoy between the base at Archangel and the Dwina river front, is that of the old windmills with their great wooden sails and picturesque bases. One is shown here silhouetted against, the sunset sky on the shortest day of the year. The sun on December 21st sets before two o'clock after only a few hours of daylight. Shengurski, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152801 December 31, 1918 (Item 8)
      (A snow shoe patrol from Company B, 339th Infantry, making its way across a field of deep snow along the shore of the Dwina River. Daily drill with the snow shoes is making the men expert in the use of them. The officers and men shown from left to right are: 1st Lieut. John Cudahy; 2nd Lieut. J.M. Calhoun; Sgt. Alfred Marcoux; Pvt. Joe Malinski; Sgt. Simon G. Davis; Pvt. Carl V. Pierson; Pvt. Daniel Davis; Pvt. B.J. Smosozynski; Corpl. W.A. Rypinski; Pvt. F. Fink (Ed.D.); Pvt. Adolph Pierce; Pvt. Luther Jacobson; Pvt. John Padpova; Pvt. J.A. Peterson; Pvt. Clarence Schen of Co. B. Chamova, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152802 January 2, 1919 (Item 9)
      (An old barn in Headquarters village Toulgas (Dwina River Front, left bank column) which serves as a billet for forty Company D men. The picture shows the winding path through the deep snow, which leads from the main road to the billet, screened from enemy observation by a row of small evergreen trees. Toulgas, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152804 January 2, 1919 (Item 10)
      ("Y" Blockhouse, one of the three most advanced American outposts at Toulgas (Dwina River Front) This blockhouse is located beyond the lines at upper Toulgas, on the main road, along which two patrols are passing, one returning from a reconnaissance in the direction of the Bolsheviki positions, the other on the way out. Passage along the road is obstructed by barbed wire entanglements. The blockhouse has a garrison of five men and is equipped with a Lewis gun. It has telephone connections with force Headquarters. Toulgas, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152805 January 3, 1919 (Item 11)
      (Thick walled emplacements in which two 3.3 guns of the Canadian Field Artillery are sheltered. These emplacements are located on the edge of a ravine which lies in the rear of Headquarters village, Toulgas. These "18 pounders" are manned by men of the 68th Battery, C.F.A. They played an important part in the repulse of a Bolsheviki attack on the village, November 11, when they fired point blank into a party of the enemy, which had attempted to carry out a flanking movement against the allied positions at Toulgas. Toulgas, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152809 January 6, 1919 (Item 12)
      (Emplacement known as No. 2, one of the strong fortifications which surround the city of Shenkurst. The city itself has a population of 2,000 and is important as the base for the forces operations on the Vaga River at Ust Padenga. This emplacement is located in an evergreen grove on the southern outskirts of the city. In time of danger it is garrisoned by 30 men. It is equipped with 2 Vikers machine guns. One corporal and four privates with a Lewis gun are on duty at all times. Note: since this picture was taken a Bolshevik force attacking the American positions along the Vaga River has occupied Shenkurst. Shenkurst, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152810 January 6, 1919 (Item 13)
      (Glimpse of the town of Shenkurst from the top of machine gun emplacement No.2. Shenkhurst is noted for the number and beauty of its churches, two of which can be seen in the background. Shenkurst, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152811 January 6, 1919 (Item 14)
      (American officer's mess, 1st Battalion headquarters Shenkurst. The officers shown in the picture from left to right are; 2nd Lt. A.L. Kelly, Co. C, 339th Inf.; 2nd Lt. B.A. Burns, Co. A, 310th Engrs.; 1st Lt. R.E. McCurdy, Co. A, 310th Engrs.; Lt. Col. Corbly, 1st Bn., 339th Inf; 2nd Lt. C.A. McNabb, Co. C, 339th Inf.; 1st Lt. Henry Katz, 339th Inf; 2nd Lt. L.L. Fay, Co. C; 2nd Lt. G.N. Weeks, Co. C, 339th Inf; 2nd Lt. C.E. Warner, Co. A, 339th Infantry. Shenkurst, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152812 January 6, 1919 (Item 15)
      (Building in which the headquarters of the 1st Battalion, 339th Inf., is located. The men in the front of the building belong to the battalion headquarters detachment. Shenkurst, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152813 January 7, 1919 (Item 16)
      (Outguard No.1, Outpost No. 1. This, the most advanced outpost of the Vaga River Column is also the most advanced of the American forces in Russia and the most distant post from the base at Archangel. In the distance can be seen the village of Pagosta which is held by the Bolsheviki. The church seen in the picture is used by the enemy as an observation post. Almost daily, machine gun fire is directed at the American outposts from that point. The man on outpost duty is Pvt. Alfred Schuck, Co. A, 339th Inf. 85th Div. Note: Two weeks from the time when this picture and other photographs of the Ust Padenga Front were taken, the Bolsheviki attacked in superior numbers and forced the Americans to abandon this point. Shenkurst, the base, 28 versts to the rear was also abandoned. The Bolsheviki continue to attack. Village Nizhnyaya-Gora at the Ust Padenga front, Vaga River Column, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152814 January 7, 1919 (Item 17)
      (Watching for signs of Bolsheviki activity in a little village across the Paderga valley to the southwest of outpost No.2. The observations are being made by Sergt. Thomas J. Rapp, at the left and Sgt. Fred Nees, both of Co. A, 339th Infantry, 85th Division, Village Nizhnyaya Gora, at the Ust Padenga, Front, Vaga River Column, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152815 January 7, 1919 (Item 18)
      (Here are shown the men of Company "A" on duty as outguard No. 1 The men are billeted in the Russian house in the background, which is only 75 yards behind outpost #1. At the head of the detail is 1st Lieut. A.F. Collar, followed by Sgt. Fred Nees, Sgt. Thomas J. Rapp, Corpl. I.N. Allikas, and Corpl. Joe Franzck of Company A. Village Nizhnyaya Gora, at Ust Padenga Front, Vaga river column, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152816 January 7, 1919 (Item 19)
      (Men composing outguard No.2, outpost No. 1, gathered in the center of the little village of Nizhnyaya Gora, in which they are billeted. At the right standing by the pony is Capt. O.A. Odjard, Co. A, 339th Infantry, commanding officer, on the Ust Padenga Front, Vaga River Column. Village Nizhnyaya Gora at the Ust Padenga Front, Vaga river column, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152818 January 7, 1919 (Item 20)
      (A view which shows the high north bank of the Padenga river which affords an excellent natural defense for the American forces. On this high ground the main line of defense rests, consisting of barbed wire entanglements, blockhouses and dugouts. Ust Padenga, Vaga River Column, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152819 January 7, 1919 (Item 21)
      (Two platoons, the 1st and 4th of Company A, 339th Infantry gathered on the snow in front of their barracks at the line. The building at one time belonged to the Imperial Government, and served as a foresters home. When the Americans took possession of it, it was serving as a hospital. Sleeping accommodations are provided in it for two platoons. Village of Vysokaya Gora, Ust Padenga. Vaga River Column. Russia.)
    - Print No. 152820 January 7, 1919 (Item 22)
      (Men of Company A, 339th Infantry, watching a boxing bout in their quarters. Boxing has been one of the chief forms of amusement during the long winter evenings. The two battlers are Sgt. Omar Yarger, (and the left) and Sgt. Robert Montgomery, Co. A, 339th Inf. Village of Vysokaya Gora, Ust Padenga, Vaga River Column, Russia.)
  - Print Nos. 152821-152839, 12 prints (Folder 6)
    - Print No. 152821 January 8, 1919 (Item 1)
      (A Bolshevik shot by an American guard at outpost No. l at 3:00 a.m. on the morning of January 8, 1919. When an enemy patrol of seven men attempted to creep up on the outpost position. This picture was taken to show the white cloak, which all the members of the patrol wore to conceal their movements in the snow. The clothing worn by the man was warm and in good condition. He carried, in addition to a hand grenade, which lies on the ground, a Remington rifle, in good condition, and a plentiful supply of ammunition. Village of Vysokaya Gora, Ust Padenga, Vaga River Column, Russia.)
    - Print No. 152822 (Item 2)
      (A blockhouse and dugout now in course of construction surrounded by barbed wire. This blockhouse is located on high ground over looking the Padenga river. When completed it will be equipped with a Vikers machine gun. One non-commissioned officer, two Vikers men and six privates will be on duty. Vysokaya Gora, Ust Padenga, Front, Vaga River Column, Russia)
    - Print No. 152823 January 8, 1919 (Item 3)